<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Andrea R. Hofer</title>
    <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://andrea-hofer.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Andrea R. Hofer</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/media/icon_huec00d3146b3662203c183d9b5f77aa22_5560949_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Andrea R. Hofer</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/admin/config.yml</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/admin/config.yml</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Purse of Her Own: Women&#39;s Access to Financial Services and Female Labor Supply</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/womensfinancialliberation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/womensfinancialliberation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;a class=&#34;btn btn-outline-primary btn-page-header&#34; href=&#34;https://www.dropbox.com/s/oyb4ce1b90oe8up/JMP_AndreaHofer.pdf?dl=0&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;
  PDF
&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In mid-20th century, US women often faced discrimination when applying for bank accounts or loans in their own names: banks frequently required male co-signers for loans and automatically transferred women?s accounts into joint accounts upon marriage. Such discriminatory practices were outlawed in different states at different times, culminating in national anti-discrimination legislation targeted at financial institutions in 1975. Exploiting the staggered introduction of these laws across states and over time, I find that independent access to financial services increased married women?s labor force participation by 4-7.5 ppt. To analyze the effects on household bargaining and divorce, I build a life-cycle model with endogenous divorce, female labor force participation, and savings decisions. Relative to a standard collective model of household bargaining, I introduce two additions: a norm cost the husband faces when his wife works, and a share of labor income that the wife can hide from the husband and use at her discretion. After calibrating the model to the US labor market in 1970, it is able to replicate the increase in female labor supply after granting women access to independent financial services. Finally, I use the model to study the effects of women?s independent control over finances on divorce and find that the probability to be divorced 10 years after marriage increases by almost 3 ppt.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Courses and teaching material</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/teaching/courses/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/teaching/courses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I have taught the following courses:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teaching assistant for the PhD course &amp;ldquo;Mathematical methods for Microeconomics&amp;rdquo; (lecturer: Andreas Hefti)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teaching assistant for the undergraduate course &amp;ldquo;Market Design&amp;rdquo; (lecturer: Marek Pycia)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teaching assistant for the course &amp;ldquo;Intorduction to Microeconomics&amp;rdquo; (lecturer: Ernst Fehr)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teaching assistant for the undergraduate course &amp;ldquo;Introduction to Macroeconomics&amp;rdquo; (lecturer: Christian Hepenstrick)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;teaching assistant for the undergraduate course &amp;ldquo;Introduction to Game Theory&amp;rdquo; (lecturer: Samuel Haefner)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I designed the following teaching materials for the Economic Education Program of the Swiss National Bank:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;How to invest and trade online&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&amp;ldquo;The economics behind Big Tech companies&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Excerpts from student evaluations&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Highly motivated and competent TA&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Very structured and clear presentations. Great instructor!&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;Highly competent TA, patient with students, open to questions and great at explaining complicated material.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cultural Attitudes and Unemployment Benefit Take Up: Evidence from the Swiss Language Border</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/unemployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/unemployment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does stigma prevent individuals from applying to unemployment benefits even if they are eligible? We exploit the cultural divide at the Swiss language border which separates German from French speaking municipalities to show that cultural values are an important determinant for unemployment take up. French-speakers&amp;ndash;who hold cultural values associated with lower stigma towards unemployment benefit take up&amp;ndash; are consistently more likely to apply for unemployment benefits within the first six months after job loss. This result holds also for workers who live on different sides of the language border but who were employed at the same firm before job loss.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mothers&#39; Labor Supply and Immigration: Evidence from the Swiss Border Opening</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/womenimmigration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/womenimmigration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does immigration affect native men and women differently? We study the case of the Swiss border opening to workers from the European Union starting in 2002 and show that while the effects do not differ for young or older men and women, there are stark differences for the age group between 30-39. We find that the gender difference in this age group is driven by young mothers leaving the labor market at higher rates after immigration. The dropout rate is largest for mothers who are married to a partner who experienced the largest wage increases due to immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Norms vs. Law Changes: What matters for Female Labor Force Participation?</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/normslaws/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/normslaws/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We study whether a signal of a norm change or the actual law change has a larger impact on real world outcomes by looking at a vote on the Swiss marriage law which passed in 1985 (signal), but was only implemented in 1988 (law change). While the old marriage law allowed the husband to prohibit his wife from working, the new law did not anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
