<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Andrea R. Hofer</title>
    <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/author/andrea-r.-hofer/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://andrea-hofer.github.io/author/andrea-r.-hofer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Andrea R. Hofer</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language>
    <image>
      <url>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/media/icon_hu658d3878f5d4721f03161a0353d38ae8_427333_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Andrea R. Hofer</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/author/andrea-r.-hofer/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Purse of Her Own: Women&#39;s Access to Banking Services and Female Labor Supply</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/womensfinancialliberation/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/womensfinancialliberation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Up until 1975, US women often reported issues when applying for bank accounts or loans in their own names: many banks required male co-signers, essentially granting married womens&#39; husbands access to their accounts. Such discriminatory practices were outlawed in the US with various credit laws introduced in different states at different times, culminating in the national Equal Credit Opportunity Act in 1975. In this paper, I study the consequences of granting married women more control over their own finances due to these law changes empirically and in a structural life-cycle model. I find that giving women full control over their own resources increases their likelihood of participating in the labor market by around 8 p.p. I enhance a standard collective household model in order to replicate my empirical findings. Calibrating the model to the US labor market shows that improving married womens&#39; financial independence contributed about % to the overall increase in female labor supply between 1970 and 1990.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mothers&#39; Labor Supply and Immigration: Evidence from the Swiss Border Opening</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/womenimmigration/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/womenimmigration/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does immigration affect native men and women differently? We study the case of the Swiss border opening to workers from the European Union starting in 2002 and show that while the effects do not differ for young or older men and women, there are stark differences for the age group between 30-39. We find that the gender difference in this age group is driven by young mothers leaving the labor market at higher rates after immigration. The dropout rate is largest for mothers who are married to a partner who experienced the largest wage increases due to immigration.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Norms vs. Law Changes: What matters for Female Labor Force Participation?</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/normslaws/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/normslaws/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;We study whether a signal of a norm change or the actual law change has a larger impact on real world outcomes by looking at a vote on the Swiss marriage law which passed in 1985 (signal), but was only implemented in 1988 (law change). While the old marriage law allowed the husband to prohibit his wife from working, the new law did not anymore.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Unemployment Insurance Uptake, Stigma and Long Run Outcomes: Evidence from the Swiss Language Border</title>
      <link>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/unemployment/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://andrea-hofer.github.io/research/unemployment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Does stigma decrease unemployment benefit uptake? We find that stigma does not affect unemployment benefit take up in good times, but has a significant effect in reducing uptake in times of economic crises.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
